Guide to the Japanese medical manuscript notebooks, 1810-1849 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Multi-Volume Sets, (37 volumes)
  - Medical manuals on obstetrics and gynecology, (11 volumes)
    - Sanka sagen / 産科瑣言, 1828 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_26)
      "Dr. Seishū's oral dictation on obstetrics and gynecology," "recorded by Sen Chōsai 1828 October 4-10, at Dr. Seishū's new school." Has a table of contents and discusses over 50 illnesses related to gynecology or obstetrics.
    - Kagawa Kōju, Vol. 1 / 賀川口授 Zen/全, 1822 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_27)
      Dr. Kagawa Gen-etsu's / 賀川元悦 oral dictation on pregnancy and delivery. This is a copy of an original version transcribed in Kansei 8 (1796) August 9, copied by Hayata Taoki (早田多冲). Short apology says that this was copied in a hurry and might contain misspellings. "Copied in Bunsei 5 [1822] early April by Yamanaka Hikooki (山中彦冲)."
    - Kagawa Kōjum, Vol. 2 / 賀川口授 Zen/全, 1822 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_28)
      Dr. Kagawa Gen-etsu's oral dictation on pregnancy and delivery. Contains two parts marked with dark blue corners.
      Section 1: Includes a preface: Chikugetsu yōtai no setsu. Shisetsu to sen kin hō no setsugō. Notes cover the care of full term pregnancy and delivery, various positions of the baby when it is delivered.
      Section 2: Has a table of contents. Main body of Kagawa Yōsai sensei kōyaku narabini Shujutsu kai [Dr. Kagawa Yōsai's oral explanation and operation commentary] starts on page 38. Compiled by Hiyō Seiden Zō / 肥陽静田増 纂輯. Contains the same note of apology as the previous volume. The original version was written in Kansei 8 [1796] August 21, copied by Hayata Taoki. The date of the volume is given as Bunsei 5 [1822] by Yamanaka Hikooki.
    - Kagawake hidan / 賀川家秘(言辺に單, 1815 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_29)
      Contents are mostly about gynecological topics. There is some insect damage but it does not affect the text. The date of the original work being copied is given as: "Kansei 7 nen [1795] rinshō [June] 5. Student Hayata, Hidetada humbly recording." The date of the notebook is given as: "Bunka 12 [1815], 12 gatsu [December]"
    - Ryōhō bakka [Best selection of good treatments] / 良方抜華, 1828 (Box 3, Volume RL_100050_V_30)
      Discusses gynecological and obstetrics ailments, with lists of symptoms, medicines, and treatments for the symptoms; 84 pages. "Bunsei 11 nen [1828] 10 gatsu [October], started Sep. 25, finished Oct. 4, Seishū sensei Shinjuku [at Dr. Seishū's new school] Shūhin / 鷲瀕."
  - Seiren hatsumō / 製煉発蒙 [Metallurgy], undated, (2 volumes)
    - Seiren hatsumō, kan no 1 [Vol. 1]/ 製煉発蒙, undated (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_31)
      Seiken Tsuboi Shindō yakujutsu / 誠軒坪井信道訳述. [Interpreted and recorded by Seiken Tsuboi Shindō] Notebook is organized into five chapters: 1) Seiren meigi shaku, [metallurgy] 2) Testing for secondary substances, 3) Combustibles and their refinement. 4) Different kinds of sodium and metallurgy, 5) Different kinds of sodium.
      Tsuboi Shindō (1795-1848) was a Japanese scholar of Dutch medicine and a doctor.
    - Seiren hatsumō, kan no 2 [Vol. 2] / 製煉発蒙, undated (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_32)
      Seiken Tsuboi Shindō shiki. [Interpreted and recorded by Seiken Tsuboi Shindō] Continued from the first volume: 6) Ronshū jikō rakutsu hōgō, 7) Ronshū jikō rakutsu endo [sodium bonded with earth] hōgōsha, 8) Rakutsu en /羅倔塩 (Japanese name for "chemical substances," using Japanese characters to imitate the sound of the word in Dutch), and rakutsu endo combined with sulfur, 9) Metals and metallurgy, and 10) untitled section.
  - Heaven and Earth medical manuals, 1829 and undated, (2 volumes)
    - Hyakuchin ikkan Ken [Heaven: vol. 1] / 百 [病だれに火] 一貫 乾, undated (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_39)
      Contents cover gynecological illnesses, pediatric medicine, asthma, and jaundice. Has a table of contents and many corrections and annotations. No date or name is given.
    - Hyakuchin ikkan Kon [Earth: vol. 2] / 百 [病だれに火] 一貫 坤, 1829 (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_40)
      The contents are similar to the first notebook, but there is no table of contents, and no comments or corrections. "Bunsei 12 [1829] January at Shunrinken new school by Sen Yōsai."
  - Opthalmology manuals, 1828 and undated, (3 volumes)
    - Ganka hiroku [Ophthalmology] 眼科秘録, undated (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_41)
      Includes a table of contents. There are a few illustrations on page 37 that include drawings of artificial eyes. No names or dates are given.
    - Ganka kibun, undated [Ophthalmology] / 眼科記聞, undated (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_42)
      The content of this book is the same as the book above. The few illustrations toward the back of the book are almost exactly the same as the previous volume, and appear in the same location (page 37). No names or dates are given.
    - Ōsaka Majima ganka densho [Ophthalmology] / 大阪馬嶌眼科傳書, 1828 (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_43)
      Short volume of ten pages, written in Shino-Japanese style. There is a diagram on page 2. "Bunsei 11 [1828] December at Shunrinken new school, by Sen Yōsai." Missing outer cover.
  - Pox and skin diseases manuals and lecture notes, undated, (3 volumes)
    - Tōshin chiyōhōron sachū [Pox] / 痘疹治用方論 鎖注, undated (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_44)
      Two manuals bound together; the second starts on page 27. The title inside refers to a doctor's name: Tai Mankō 戴曼公. Recorded by a student, Ikeda Seichoku; several other names are given. Topics include medicinal herb teas, baths, pills, and powders for pox and skin irritations. Each manual has a few sections: small brown papers on the upper corners of the pages indicate subtitles. Written in Shino-Japanese style.
    - Tōshin chijutsu den / 痘疹治術傳, Tōshin fujin ka / 痘疹婦人科, Tōshin hyakushi den / 痘疹百死傳, Yōyōsai Ikeda hōkan / 幼幼斎 池田方凾, dates uncertain (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_45)
      Contains four sections on pox and other skin diseases as the cover titles indicate. Each section has its own page number sequence.
      Section 1: Tōshin chijutsu den, written by Min Tai Mankō. Original date written: "Enpō 5 [1677] September humbly recorded by Ikeda Seichoku."
      Section 2: This section does not carry the title Tōshin fujin ka, but the words in this section suggest that it is about pregnant women with pox. Undated.
      Section 3: Tōshin hyakushi keijō den [The pox: one hundred forms of death]. Written by Dr. Min Tai Mankō. "Kansei 5 [1793] copied at Yōyōsai juku." The earlier date derives from the original version that was later copied.
      Section 4: Yōyōsai Ikeda hōkan. Includes a list of 97 medicines on the first two pages. The next page has section titled "Hatsunetsu giji hō" that goes up to page nineteen and is dated Kansei 7 [1795] August 18. Copied by the student Juikidō shujin Tanobe (or Tabiki) Muro. The earlier date refers to the original version that was later copied.
      Tai Mankō 戴曼公 was a Zen monk and doctor from Ming China (1596 to 1672) who established residency in Japan. He was especially known for the treatment of pox. His alternate name is Dokuryū Shōeki (独立性易).
    - Seisetsu tōsō kibun / 西説痘瘡記聞, undated (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_46)
      This lecture notebook covers pox and eczema and their treatments. "Dr. Kashizono Koishi's oral instruction. Received by the student Ryū Tenka." An additional lecture by Koishi begins on page 22. Includes a table of contents.
      Koishi Genzui 小石元瑞 also known as Kashizono Koishi (1784-1849) was a doctor in the later Edo period who studied with Sugita Genpaku (杉田玄白), the doctor and author of Kaitai shinso (解体新書). Genpaku was the Dutch scholar who first translated the Dutch medical work, Ontleedkundige Tafelen into Japanese.
  - Herbal and medicinal manuals, 1847 and undated, (2 volumes)
    A two-volume set generally discussing herbal compounds and other medicines.
    - Kujusai hōfu, Kan no jō [Vol. 1] / 駆豎斎方府, 1847 (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_48)
      The preface was written by Morioka Jii, Yasumi Takatō / 八角高遠 in Shino-Japanese style in Kōka 4 [1847] February. The table of contents lists 21 sections in a different hand. Contents include a list of ailments and the method of manufacturing herbal remedies for each illness.
      Kujusai and Onikuni are alternative names; this physician's official name is Shingū Ryōtei / 新宮凉庭 (1787-1854); he studied with Dutch physician, Feruke-Baptiste. Yasumi Takatō [1816-1886] was a Western-style medical doctor.
    - Kujusai hōfu, Kan no ge [Vol. 2] / 駆豎斎方府, undated (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_49)
      The notebook is organized in eight sections selected by Dr. Onikuni; centers on the method of compounding different types of medicines. The names of several editors are given in the text.
- Single manuscript notebooks, (26 volumes)
  These manuals and lecture notes stand as individual works. When possible, titles are taken from the covers or from section headings; approximate translations in English in brackets were provided by library staff. Titles and significant names are also given in Japanese characters.
  - Seibidō hōketsu / 済美堂方訣, undated (Box 1, Volume RL_100050_V_10)
    Only the table of contents is present; the rest of the notebook has been lost. The name Seibidō refers to a medical practice in Kyoto of physician Takenaka Bunpō (竹中文輔) (1766-1836). As with many other volumes in this collection, this is a copy of an original medical manual by Takenaka Bunpō, copied by Yamanaka Hideyuki, probably a medical student at Seibidō.
  - Shunrinken kasho [Shunrinken school family book] / 春林軒 家書, 1810, 1828 (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_18)
    The notebook is profusely illustrated with hand-colored drawings of osteopathic manipulations, cotton dressing materials, and bandages applied to different parts of the body. The last half contains illustrations of an operation to remove cancerous breast tissue, and commentary. The end of that section is signed Bunka 7 [1810] by Jukusei Bigo Nomura Gaku / 塾生 備後 野村鄂. The next page is signed by a student from Bizen, Akaishi Kihan / 赤石希范 in Bunsei Tsuchinoto Mi, May 31." The last page is signed and stamped: "Copied [by] Tangetsu" / 端月.
    Shunrinken (春林軒) is the name of Dr. Seishu's medical school. Kasho means "family book," which refers to the intellectual legacy of the "family" Hana ke (華家) (a shortened form of Hanaoka, the famous physician). The date is probably incorrectly written, because Tsuchinoto Mi is the second year of Kōka era rather than the Bunsei era [1845]. It is more likely the year Tsuchinoe Ne [1828] in the Bunsei era.
  - Hana ke seikotsu bakutai no zu / 華家 整骨縛帯之図, undated (Box 2, Volume RL_100050_V_19)
    This volume contains similar illustrations of bandages and osteopathic cases as in the Shunrinken Kasho volume, but in black-and-white instead of color. The back cover shows signs of insect damage. This volume is slightly bigger than Shunrinken Kasho but fewer pages; it may be a draft of that volume.
  - Hōyo / 方輿, 1829 (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_33)
    Divided into three categories: gynecological, pediatric, and adult ailments. Chiefly consists of lists of medicines and their uses. "Bunsei 12 [1829] Shōgatsu [January], transcribed by Sen Yōsai at Shunrin-ken shinjuku."
  - Hōyo kibun / 方輿記聞, undated (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_34)
    The contents of this notebook are very similar to the Hōyo in the previous folder, but includes a few more ailments; no date or name is given.
  - Satsuyōhō / 撮要方, 1828 (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_35)
    This 96-page notebook includes lists of ailments and herbal treatments and corrections in red ink. "Bunsei 11 [1828] August 21-27 by Sen Chōsai at Dr. Seishū's new school."
  - Satsuyōhō sen / 撮要方筌, undated (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_36)
    The contents are the same as previous volume but without corrections. Also 96 pages long, with table of contents; no date or name is given.
  - Seinō hiroku / 青嚢秘録, 1828 (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_37)
    The first three chapters are about how to make certain drugs, including narcotics, and aroma therapy. Chapter 2 mentions an anaesthetic, Mafutsutō / 麻沸湯, that Hanaoka developed from datura. The rest of the chapters are about ailments such as skin diseases, animal bites, bruises, and treatments with herbal medicines. There is a table of contents and corrections and comments in red ink. "Bunsei 11 [1828] November by Yamanaka, Hideyuki at Dr. Seishū's new school."
  - Yōkahō sen / 瘍科方筌, 1828 (Box 4, Volume RL_100050_V_38)
    Subjects in this volume cover tumors, boils, and notes on an abscess and its treatment with herbal medicine. Ingredients for compounds are listed. There is a table of contents. The main text bears corrections and comments in red ink. "Bunsei 11 [1828] July early in the month to 18th. Jissinsai 日新斎 (Shimazu Tadayoshi) Yamanaka, Shūsai Hideyuki."
  - Chitō yōhō / 治痘用方, date uncertain (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_47)
    Tōshin chijutsuden / 痘疹治術伝: lecture by Dr. Min Tai Mankō, recorded by student Ikeda Seichoku. The first nine pages are a case study dated Enpō 5, Hinoto Mi [1677] September by Ikeda Seichoku. The next section is titled: "Dr. Min Tai Mankō Chitō yōhō recorded by Ikeda Seichoku, selected by Genson Seikyō." A postscript reads "Kansei 4 [1792] Spring February by Ikeda, Zuisen." After this, there are several pages of supplementary comments.
  - Kujusai isoku katsuyō [Dr. Kujusai's selection of the principles of medicine] / 駆豎斎 医則括要, undated (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_50)
    The title of this book appears on the third page following the preface. Contains general remarks on the practice of medicine, with summaries of the main classes of medical practice, and a section with the characteristics of various medicines. Recorded by Moribe Hōshuku.
  - Tōka idan [Medical talk under the lamp] / 燈下医談, 1828 (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_51)
    Includes a table of contents of 189 illnesses or topics. Some illness listed are accompanied by brief medical commentary. "Bunsei 11 [1828] October 11-17. Copied at Dr. Seishū's new school by Shūhin."
  - Kenshō hyakumon fukō [One hundred probing questions on illnesses] / 険症百問 附考, 1828 (Box 5, Volume RL_100050_V_52)
    This is chiefly a manual on medicinal practice in the form of reflections and questions. Title is taken from inside cover. Preface is written in Shino-Japanese style by Nomura Gaku. There are revisions noted in red ink. Date: Bunsei 11 [1828] September 1-5 by Sen Chōsai. The second part bears the title Kenshō hyakumon kō [reflections], written by Hara Genkō." "Bunsei 11 [1828] December, copied by Sen Chōsai at Dr. Seishū's new school."
    Yoshimasu Nangai (1750-1813) was a medical doctor in the middle to later Edo period. Hara Genkō's full name was Hara Genkō Masakatsu; he was a samurai doctor in Mito Han.
  - Iso Kihaku kō [Reflections on Kihaku, the founder of medical science] / 医祖岐伯考, 1829 (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_53)
    Approximately 36 pages long, written in Kanji and Katakana. Date: Bunsei 12 [1829] November. Written by Minamoto no Matsuura Dōho Genrei, who indicates he was 29 years old when he wrote this book.
    Kihaku 岐伯 was a legendary Chinese physician. Minamoto no Matsuura Dōho Genrei / 源松浦道輔原禮 (1801-1866) practiced medicine until 1824 but later became a scholar of ancient Japanese thought and culture.
  - Kyorō rōsai [tuberculosis] meigi no ben / 虛労労際名義辨, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_54)
    Dr. Koishi Hekika's 小石碧霞 oral instruction, written by student Shō Ryōsai / 鷦鷯斎. On the last page, in red ink, there are notes regarding three early symptoms of incurable tuberculosis.
    Koishi Hekika, (1743-1809), late Edo period Dutch medicine doctor, was commonly known as Koishi Genshun / 小石元俊. Dr. Ransai is Kagawa Ransai / 賀川蘭斎 (1771-1833), a late Edo period doctor and obstetrician.
  - Yōka sagen / 瘍科瑣言, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_55)
    The table of contents lists 116 illnesses, including tumors, cancers, and carbuncles. No date or name is given.
  - [Untitled volume on treating tumors] / （病だれに水）書, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_56)
    There is no title on the outer cover, but a form of title is given at the table of contents and the end page. Includes a table of contents with 36 entries regarding tumors. The notes describe how to brew medicinal herbs using specific ingredients for treating tumors. Koishidō Yūso is the same person as Koishi Genshun and Koishi Hekika.
  - Tansendō shuchū ihō [Tansendō's medical method] / 丹晴堂手中医方, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_57)
    Covers the common cold, fevers, fire and hot water burns, bruises, scabies, sword wounds, and more. Explanations of the symptoms are listed, followed by herbal treatments. Includes a table of contents. Written by Nishiyama Joho, a student from Izumo. Mentions the name of Minato Chōan 湊長安 (1786-1838), a second-generation pupil of Sugita Genpaku, the first Dutch medical scholar in Japan. Tansendō was his medical school.
  - Juikidō keikenhō [Juikidō's method based on experience] / 壽域堂経験方, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_58)
    Contains 99 recipes for medicinal tea ingredients and dosing information, mostly all Chinese formulas. There are some corrections or notes in red ink. No name or date is given. There are occasional deletions of text by the use of either white powdered seashell or white lead.
  - Satsubyō soku [Rules to identify illness] / 察病則, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_59)
    Fourteen-page notebook written in Shino-Japanese style. The first page has a list of factors to consider in patients, such as age, occupation, stability of their emotional state, and other data; this is followed by a list of normal heart rates (pulse) of healthy people by age from nine months to sixty. The main section contains a list of medical herbs and their uses for particular illnesses. No name or date is given.
  - Kinsō kōketsu [Lecture on sword wounds] / 金瘡口訣, 1828 (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_60)
    The table of contents lists thirty entries: topics cover sword wounds, suturing techniques with illustrations, gunshot wounds, hemostatic method and treatment including poultices, ointments and oral medicines. Also contains measurements for cotton bandages needed for different parts of the body. The upper third of the page was used for notes, a few of which include small illustrations of suturing. On the last page: "This lecture was copied at Dr. Seishū's new school in Bunsei 11 [1828] October 18-23 by Yamanaka Shūsai Hideyuki. Mr. Tsuzuki proofread this book following the 24th."
  - Hoei suchi [Everything you should know about keeping a baby healthy] / 保嬰須知, undated (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_61)
    Written by Soshū Ishi [medical doctor of Sagami no kuni], [and?] Katakura Genshū Shinpo / 片倉元周深甫. This forty-five page manual on pediatrics was written in Shino-Japanese style. There is one illustration of a young male child on page twenty. Page 34 has come loose from the binding.
    Katakura Genshū (1751-1822) used the name Shinpo in formal situations. He also used the name Kakuryō 鶴陵 as his nickname. He was a medical practitioner in the late Edo period who introduced the use of western obstetrical forceps.
  - Ketsuron ketsueki [Theory of blood] / 血論, 1849 (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_62)
    This notebook is organized into eleven chapters on hematology, the science of blood. Includes readings of a man's pulse taken three times a day over five days. Written by Shingū Seki Ryōtei / 新宮碩凉庭. "Kaei 2 [1849] April by Seki 石." A note reads, "Karan reki [Western calendar] 1748."
    Shingū Seki Ryōtei (1787-1854) used as his formal name Seki; he was also known as Onikuni Yamahito. He was a physician in Kyōto and founder of medical school, Junsei shoin, in 1839.
  - Shiken hō [Testing methods] / 試験方, 1829 (Box 6, Volume RL_100050_V_63)
    One of the longest notebooks at 154 pages, covering 56 illnesses and their symptoms, treatments, and medicinal herbs. There are dried leaves laid into the folds of pages 60 and 94. In the last page an explanation reads: "Shiken hō is said to be written by Kyōto's Doctor Fukui. This book is of Kashū Kanazawa Yoshioka Jōhei's [Ishikawa prefecture, Kanazawa, Yoshioka Johei] in which the illnesses are arranged by categories, then treatment methods are listed under each illnesses so it will be useful for searching. Thus it is not the same book as Fukui's original book. But since we couldn't find any better one, I copied this one here." "Bunsei 12 [1829] Jan. at Shunrinken new school by Sen Chōsai."